Thank you everyone for joining. Um, I
know it is an absolute scorcher of a day
and you could be in a pub garden right
now having a few beers, but you're here
listening to me about AI native
development. So, I give you my thanks
and I also question your life choices,
but here we are. Um, so we're going to
be talking about how we navigate this
new thing that we're calling AI native
development. what it is. We'll talk
through a number of things including
what what we are now calling codecentric
development which before AI I guess we
just called coding and development um
and and how we use AI to empower
ourselves and get further uh with with
code ccentric. We're going to also talk
a little bit about some of the lessons
that we've learned at Tessle um because
at Tessle we're building some cool AI
native development platform and and we
do a lot of prompting. try and get a lot
of generation and testing uh coming out
of a number of models. So our AI
engineering team have have you know
given us a bunch of learnings that we
want to make sure we share with as many
people as possible as well. Then we flip
it around really and we talk about well
what is spec centric? What is how do we
how do we build software via spec as our
source of you know our source of truth.
Um what does that look like? How does it
change the way we develop software? And
then finally look at why AI native. What
else does it bring us that that uh a
code ccentric world doesn't provide us
with?
Cool. My name is Simon Mabel. I I'm one
of the founding devs at Tesla and um
yeah, Tesla's a just over one-year-old
company right now. Um everyone anyone
heard of Sneak SNK?
Does anyone know what it means?
Kind of. No. No. What it means though?
Sneak. So now you know. It's the biggest
secret which is an ironic way of like so
now you know but no one knows. Um so so
the founder of sneak guy Pagani moved
over to Tessle um brought a number of
people actually from uh from ex sneakers
from the ex sneak founding team. Um I
was one of the lucky ones who who kind
of like joined uh early with a number of
other people who are in this room and
yeah AI native development is what we're
building. Okay let's uh start off with
codeentric and we'll talk about how we
build code. uh we can still build
applications in a co-cententric way with
AI. I built this application actually
for um uh a workshop uh a conference
called Open UK. Anyone open UK here this
year? Just Sammy who was organizing it.
So that doesn't count. Um okay. Uh let's
jump over to an app that I created. As I
mentioned, I created this using uh using
Bolt. And the idea is it's just um an
application that takes in some prompts,
generates code from the prompts. it can
iterate through that code based on the
prompts I I provide it with and then
every single time code is generated it
runs a set of tests against it. So I can
use my prompt to make my code uh cater
for a greater number of scenarios
eliminate bugs add some more bugs etc
etc. In this case, uh the system prompt
here just says, you know, the usual,
you're a JavaScript coder, blah blah
blah. Um, and the goal of this is to
create a pluralizer function. So,
generate uh a function called pluralizer
that takes a English word and pluralizes
it. So as my chat I might say uh create
a function
that plur that takes uh takes a word
and
you can see how bad my typing is now and
pluralizes is this is the text okay for
the back yeah all good and pluralizes
that word and yes I am writing in US
English today because I don't want to
confuse it with the function name Um,
okay. So, it's created that. That looks
short but reasonable. Um, 18 of my tests
have passed. I can see at this stage
what is passing, what is failing. Um, it
looks like right now there's a number of
exception words and other knife to
knives, wolf to wolves and other
patterns that it's missed when we
prompt. One thing that's really really
important, there are certain times when
we want an exception word whereby there
is no rule here. this is the word I want
to get if you get this word. When we
write sometimes tests and generate code
from tests or when we give it specific
examples, very often it will say, oh,
I'll write code that fixes that exact
example. Whereas when we prompt, we
actually want to get it to do something
more generic. want to say um I might say
something I mean I could just say
something very generic here like um take
into account the um
F
and F endings rule and apply this and
apply these cases in my function and
then what it will do
is it will let's see what It's done.
Okay. So, it's changed F to Ves and FE
to VES. And hopefully, can anyone
remember what my number was before?
18. So, it's added five successful tests
and so forth. Um, there we go. Look,
some of those are fixed. I might also
say add exception cases.
Exception cases and words that do not
change.
who um who isn't a native English
speaker here. Oh, I really feel for you
because when you write this, you realize
how bastardized the English language is
and how hard it is to um Okay, so we
test that. Oh, look what it's done now.
It's added some wonderful English for
me. So, I've updated the code. Thank you
very much.
Okay, I just hit update code and now 27
of my tests have passed. And you can see
now I'm adding greater and greater
cases. However, what's the what's the
source of truth here? Let's see. Um,
everything that I've added um in this in
this chat is very disposable. Okay,
every single time I put a prompt in, it
takes me from two place. It takes me
from one place to another place. The
version of code before that prompt was
written and to the version of code
afterwards. If I apply that prompt, if I
use that prompt at any other time, it
doesn't make sense because it only
applies to the state that existed on
that first version. So everything here
is disposable. It's throw away. Okay, I
can't get back to this stage unless I
have that initial state followed by
these prompts and the AI in a
deterministic way, which we know it
doesn't work like that, does the same
thing every single time. So this is all
throwaway and even I wanted to reuse it,
I can't. The source of truth is the
code. Okay, so this is how AI is getting
me to that place faster where this this
is still codecentric. I check in the
code, I maintain the code, I manage the
code. AI is just helping me write that
code.
Okay. Who's used C-Pilot? Who hasn't
used C-pilot? Really? That surprises me.
I was I was going to not demo Copilot
and I'm still not going to because
that's your fault, right? Everyone
should have used Copilot by now. Um
Copilot. Okay. was one of the original I
I'm not going to say the original, it's
by far not the original, but probably
the original mainstream coding assistant
that you can just tab prompts in your in
your browser as you type away. Um, but
it was quite simple. It very often just
did one line or a few lines, then went
onto a function and now it actually does
more and more things. One of the kind of
bigger players, um, let's go to this
one. One of the bigger players is
Cursor, of course. Who's used Cursor?
That's a far more interesting tool.
Cursor does obviously things like
multi-file changes which GitHub now does
as well. Um but it has this kind of like
this chat that allows me to interact
with it, ask questions, um you know do
much more complex changes through this
more agentic style. Um this is an
example. I think this was this is uh for
those who watch the podcast this was
actually the example code that a guy
called Joe
we just call him Joe. Joe Joe he's just
Joe to everyone. Uh he's like he's like
again wholecraft. Yeah, he's like Kylie
or Madonna. It's just one name we know
him as. So Joe wrote this using um uh
Bolt for yeah not Bolt44. Bolt new. I
use base 44. And I can just import this
and go ahead and make some changes. This
is actually like a Sim City style thing.
I might make a change. Maybe I'll just
say um make sure there are uh buildings
um of many different
costs
and levels.
Okay. When I make that suggestion, it
goes away. It thinks about a bunch of
stuff. It works out what it needs to
change. It applies those changes. It
does it to multiple files. And as Matt
was saying, we just blindly ignore what
it says, hit accept all, and then vibe
code through our test. I think that's
what I learned from you. And then you
just go push to production, right? Yeah.
Perfect. That's what I learned. So,
yeah,
I knew you'd love that, Richard. Um, so
yeah, it's it's made some changes to
index, it's made changes to game
reduces, etc., etc. I just hit accept
all push. All good. Um, now there's
something else that I'm going to show
you, which is bolt new. This is kind of
like VI coding where it's very
codecentric. It shows you the changes.
You maybe run some tests afterwards. we
are very much in your IDE and this is of
course VS Code or a fork of VS Code. Um
however the next step beyond that is
vibe coding where we don't actually look
at the code. We're not focused on the
code but it's vibe coding where we're
almost like click testing. Um so this is
much more of a kind of like a bolt. So
if I were to come back here and go to
bolt new what I might say here is who
who wants to build a name a simple app?
I can't. All right. Okay. No. Uh, an
app. Create an app.
Create an app that interrupts
interrupts someone's flow. Someone's
flow with a random noise like a can
opening. Perfect. That was like we did
we needed no words for that, didn't we?
We're on the same level here. I can
tell. So, what Bolt will do is now Bolt
will go ahead and start it thinks. It
loves thinking, using all my tokens up,
thinking, thinking, thinking. It'll
probably tell me what it's going to do
using more tokens. There it goes. Um,
and it is going to create this this
structure of an application and then
start building that out. I could click
on the code and start looking through
all the changes. One of the core things
about the way Bolt um builds is, as you
can see, it's writing me a whole ton of
code. I don't think still today, maybe
people can who use this more than me can
keep me up to date, keep me honest with
this. I don't think it will really share
with me too much of a of a um of a diff
here. Um whereas cursor kind of like
that says, "These are your changes. Do
you want to accept them?" This may only
change one line or a couple of lines,
but it will rewrite the entire file. It
makes it quite hard to to to almost like
see what's see what's changing. In this
case, it's created some initial files,
installed some dependencies using npm
install. I'm gonna have to actually my
volume. Oh no. Right. I'll mute that. Um
it's updating this application. Couple
of interesting points about bolt. It's
very opinionated about the things it
uses. So things like Superbase as a
great example. If you wanted to use some
persistent storage, it will it will kind
of like it has a wonderful integration
with Superbase where not only can I just
use it with a few clicks, but it will
also make changes to the necessary
changes to permissions, size, table
sizes, and things like that. Um, it also
has an awesome integration with Netflix.
Not Netflix, sorry. Netlefy. Um,
Netlefy. Uh, oh, look at this. Amazing.
Um, it it will create me um I can just
one click publish up to Netify. Even if
I don't have a um an account already, it
will do it for free and then as I want
to take it on, I can push it over to my
account and so forth. So, here's a flow
interrupter. Amazing. Look at that. uh
tells me how many interruptions and
excellent right so I'm gonna hit start
you might need to echo Okay.
[Music]
Come on. Come on. Come on. Come on.
Right. I'll turn that off. Okay. We get
the idea. If I wanted to make changes, I
would literally make changes as as text
here. It would update this system. Where
do I have I looked at the code? Have I
seen the code change? No. I go forward
and click that. I might say I want the
defaults to change to blah and blah. I
want these these additional controls. I
want different sounds that I can choose.
Would I go into the would am I asking it
to create tests? Has it got any tests?
Absolutely not. Right. This is a
completely different It's the same vibe
coding, but it's a completely different
level. I'm looking at it from the from
the UI, not the code as much. Cool.
Keeps interrupting you, by the way. It
does. Thank you. Thank you for that
interruption by the way. I appreciate
it. Um Okay, cool.
One last thing that I'm going to I'm
going to talk about. Um,
nothing in here.
Uh, we mentioned Claude Code. Anyone use
Claude Code? Super cool. If you haven't
used it, have a play. It's amazing. Um,
okay. I'm in an empty uh empty directory
here. I'm going to write Claude. It says
welcome to Claude Code. Uh, create a new
app or clone a repository and do these
other things. I'm just going to say
let's create an app that takes uh that
um
no let's create a script uh that
uh create a script with our dice roll
function that takes
uh dice roll notation
for example
uh let's say 2D6
what this means is two dice with six
sides. So
if I wanted to total this, it might be
12 between 12 and two. Um and return me
the return me the um total.
So
uh the first thing you'll notice it's
entirely terminal based. Um it will
create me some stuff. Uh it oh this got
this awesome to-do stuff, awesome to-do
list where it can kind of like go
through all the tasks it's going to do.
It checks them off. Things like that.
It's gambling, which is pretty cool. So,
it's obviously gone to some some site to
gamble. Um, do you want to create dice
roll py? Damn, it's doing in Python.
Okay.
So, that looks good. It does some
calculating. Look at the tokens flying
up there. Um, create dice. Okay. Has it
done it? It's done it. Um, let's test
the dice roll
function. There are no tests created.
It's only source created. But if I was
to say create some tests, it would do
that for me. Uh, I run that. Do I want
to execute this bash command? Yes.
Command not found. Python.
Oh, it's I got Python 3. Yeah.
Okay. The dice roll function works
correctly. So, it's run several tests.
Well, it's run it several times with an
expectation. Um, and it seems to work
out. Okay. Interesting. 3d8 plus2. I've
never seen that before. Oh, okay. It's
just done some math on the end. Weird.
Okay. Um, cool. So, that's this is kind
of like clawed code. Very very
interesting in the terms of being able
to use this in a workflow as well
because it's because it's just CLI. I
love the kind of the flow of this where
you can actually then invoke this from
other places. Um, but yeah, pretty
pretty cool. Um, and of course now on my
local machine, I've got that. I can
count it. Um,
and you can see the code it's produced.
But we don't want to see code now, do
we? No. No. We just want to see it
works. Um, okay. Cool. The problem with
all of this, well, not problem, but the
an interesting thing that we need to
remember about this is everything here
is codecentric.
Everything I've done gets me to to the
position of code quicker. Um, and
actually takes me away from potentially
some of the the things that would guard
me from problems in code because I'm
going to code faster, ignoring a lot of
the usual steps, the good steps that
Matt was kind of like talking about
there.
Before we jump on to more specs, I want
to talk a little bit about prompts and
the way that I've been writing prompts
here, which is kind of like a you give
the minimum possible on the podcast. Um
uh Dez Trainer uh one of the co-founders
of Intercom said this beautiful line
which I always forget and misquote but
it's something along the lines of the
ability to short prompt meaning the
ability for us to be able to write
something short and actually get the LLM
to do something for us robs us of that
ability to actually give an LLM detailed
information about what we actually want.
So because I can write something short
and get away with it, I do it and I'm
actually I'm actually not putting the
information that I need very often. So
when we think about prompting
um there's a there's a number of times
that prompting won't actually help um
for example maybe I don't know context
is too large maybe we need to give it
too many too many um too many rounds of
iteration for example sometimes context
windows are very very important now
context windows for models are
absolutely huge these days and if you
give that much information the LM stands
virtually no chance of understanding
which bit of information it should use
to actually provide you with In fact,
you don't even need to go close to the
the context sizes. You will notice that
if you probably go through like a
quarter or something like that, you or
or a third, you'll probably see your
your value actually degragating from
from that. So, the attention decay um is
is important. Um sublevel token tasks or
yes, sub subtoken level tasks rather. Um
who's tried to do a code diff with an
LLM? How successful was it? Not
successful at all because tokens
actually span more than one character,
right? So, it's very very hard for it to
identify what the changes are. Um, word
manipulations. Here are here are three
anagrams. Um,
none of them are anagrams. In fact,
these two are blatantly not anagrams.
This is the same text twice, which is I
mean, I suppose an anagram tester would
say it's an anagram, but it's it's not
an anagram, right? Um, it's not great
with things like words. It's not great
with things like math. We know this,
okay? We know there are functions and
things that we can use to um it's
testing this as a string for example
right we know this um no no sorry it's
not it's taking that as 11 rather than
rather than nine um a couple of other
things how LLM's read your prompt did
you know an LM starts processing its
response before it actually finishes the
prompt that you've asked it finishes the
response before you've finished reading
that prompt what that means is the most
important things that you write are at
the very start because if you've left
something really important till the end
and it's actually already constructing
that response
you're potentially missing certain
things. Let me give you an example.
There's two solutions to this actually.
Before I give you that example, two
solutions. One is well, let's do this
thing called prompt sandwiching. Um
whereby this is very much like talking
to a child, right? If I was to get ask
my nine-year-old not to play with a
football indoors, I'll say something
like, "Right, don't play with that
football if he picks it up. Oh, and can
you make this thingy over here and stop
playing with that football because it's
important at the start? it's important
to remind them at the end and so this is
actually a very common way of asking
that LLM to do something either side.
Now when we structure prompts a real
interesting way that we have done this a
couple of times with in tessle is we're
not talking about strict XML or I think
we did that in the early stages but we
use XML tags in our in our prompts so
that this structure whereby we say these
are the provided materials this is the
specification here's some template code
you can you can refer to other pieces
within the specification very very
easily and the LLM loves that structure
this is a far better way of getting an
accurate response than if you just put
it as one massive code block. So
structured prompts work as well. Now
this is something that Macy Baker uh for
those of you um who I guess watch the
podcast a little bit and and follow our
blog um talked about which is called
task framing. And if we think back to
that um that that fact that an LLM
starts responding starts creating that
result before it finishes working out
your prompt. When we think about
constraints,
this constraint here, do not use any
external dependencies for a prompt that
is asking for something that you know a
piece of software component whereby what
it absolutely wants to do is use
software components. For example, what
is this uh JavaScript package? It's a
markdown specification. Yeah. Okay. It's
not really saying what it is, but um
typically there are a ton of examples
out that this LLM has trained on which
uses third party dependencies. If I'm
telling it not to use third party
dependencies at the end, by the time
it's already started reading this and
constructing its answer, it's already
thinking about and using, you know, data
that it can that constructs that with
third party dependencies. When we run
this, we pretty much always got a result
that used third third party
dependencies. So, what could we do?
Well, because we know the very top is
the most is the is one of the most
important parts of our prompt, we could
move this to the top. But what task
framing is about is about asking the LLM
to do something. Framing that task in a
way whereby your constraint becomes the
way that you speak, the way that you ask
for something. So, do not use any
external dependencies turns into a
self-contained JavaScript package. It's
not a constraint, it's the description
of the style of package that I want to
use. It's self-contained. It's not going
to use third party dependencies.
That's task framing. Um few other tips
before we move on. Um
yeah, don't the more detail you provide
it with, the more constrained you you're
expecting it to find results in a
smaller set of information. I would say
only provide it with the constraints
with the things that you care about. If
you LM are great at filling in the gaps,
only say the things that you're super
care about and then maybe over
iterations and other things, you're able
to kind of like make smaller changes. Um
there's a couple of other things there,
but the model say is really really
interesting. When we were um priming the
the uh the models with context, we
noticed that when we tried to do it all
in one go, it would give us a whole load
of about oh that's a very
interesting problem. Let me think about
this and da da da. Well, actually we
want just the answer. For example, when
I asked for when I asked for the uh that
code example, it said oh here I've
updated that code blah blah blah. What
model say is this is actually very
similar to my kids because you say this
thing and then you just throw away the
response. All right, that's what that's
what my kids do. They tell me something
and then I say something back and they
just ignore me completely.
What the the the fact why this is
important is because we're adding
context into this into this desri into
this discussion with an LLM. Then as
soon as we want something, we ask a very
straightforward question and capture the
response and we get just that response.
Okay, so it's really a really important
way of getting just the response piece
that we need priming the LLM with
context previously.
Okay. Whoa. So, some prompt takeaways.
Um, modularization is really important
as well. Make sure the scope of what
you're asking for is small and then kind
of like combine, you know, exactly like
we build software today, software
components that reuse each other. Let's
um let's make sure that's that's
modularized. And exactly the same with
uh prompts as well.
Um,
and yeah, I think one of the key things
here is as well, don't use LLMs for
everything. Recognize what you can use
LLMs for, where you should use them, and
and and have a balance between LLM usage
within your app as well as outside.
So, we'll walk we'll take a little step
away from code centricity now and we'll
talk about what spec centricity is. Um
now
I want to take you first of all
uh into back to this kind of like prompt
scenario where I prompt generate some
generate some code run some tests
against it. This time we're going to do
it in a spec way and in a spec way
um there's a couple of things here. I
have a specification that code is
generated from that specification but
that doesn't mean I can't use prompts
because I might use the specification
assistant to help me generate that
specification. So this is still
disposable because you know I'm throwing
away the the actions I make between the
versions of my spec. But the
specification itself is the thing that
should last. The specification itself is
my source of truth. Code that then gets
generated from it is just generated
code. It's a code from the moment in
time that this specification existed. So
I might have a template and that
template might say I want some
functionality. What are the what are the
what are the things I care about uh this
this function doing? I might have an API
definition take a word in respond with a
word. I might have a number of test
cases as well as part of my
specification. Then when you know all of
this, generate the code from there. I
might say uh create a specification
specification
um that takes that creates a pluralize
function.
um which takes
a word as input
and plur pluralizes
it.
Okay, it makes some changes. It gave me
a functionality, some API definition,
some test cases. Now, interestingly,
it's given me some test cases which it
might, if I just click generate from
spec here, we'll see what it does. It
might Yeah, I know it's actually done
pretty well.
unchanged.
Wow, that is surprising how good that
is. First, so first time around, 51% of
an absolutely abysmal language. Not bad.
And I don't mean JavaScript, I mean
English. Um although yeah. Um now when I
make changes, whether through the prompt
or through this,
this retains the my my my current state.
I can now generate whatever I want from
this. Maybe I want a Java application
that does this. it doesn't change my
specification I don't think maybe
certain words like function and things
like that but if I did this in a in a
language agnostic open API way or
something like that you know I could I
could do that across different languages
and so forth maybe even different uh
spoken languages as well for
pluralization and things like that
um
okay let's jump into
why or or how specifications change the
way we're going to work. So, LLMs, yeah,
they're magical. If I say create a
simple page, which is a to-do app, it
provides me with this simple page as of
a to-do app. I type a to-do in, I hit
add. Does it work? Of course, it
doesn't. So, I say clicking add does
nothing. It implements it. Clicking add
does something wonderful.
But, of course, why change the damn
button color? I didn't ask you to change
the button color, but it does it. Um,
and is it wrong? No, it's not wrong
because I haven't asked for it not to be
blue or I haven't asked for it to be
blue specifically.
Where is this decision captured today?
Well, code couples the what and the how?
It has the intent and it has the
implementation. So, if I was to look at
someone else's code, did they do that
because that's just how they chose to do
it? Did they do that because that's
design? It's part of a requirement. I
don't know. I'm going to change it and
I'm going to break it anyway. That's
that's that's why I'm a developer
advocate these days, not a developer.
But code couples the intent, the what
and the implementation, the how. That's
that's core to to to what we're going to
be talking about. So software
development is code centric. We start
off with a requirements document, a
wonderful PD somewhere. We generate some
code from that. And of course the the
requirements document is perfect and has
every edge case written by someone who
understands exactly, you know, how to
develop software and build software. So
we create this code first time around.
Boom. YOLO. We package that code. We
create some documentation. We probably
write some tests. When we think about
the what's disposable, what's longived,
the disposable pieces, the requirements.
Yes, that will go out of date so
quickly. The code becomes the longived
thing and the source of truth. And
typically these are paired pretty well
because they'll typically run in some
CI/CD.
Um the docs is descriptive of some
version of my code. And then this will
typically be built every time. Of
course, we release an enhancement comes
in. No problem. I'll fix the code. No
one touches the requirements. Docker
course. This has come in through some
issue or some other feature. We update
the code. Bug fix. Yeah, I'll fix that.
No problem. Edge case. Oh Yeah,
you can you can have specific cases. Oh,
Latin plurals. I see. I see. Okay. Yeah,
I'll add that. Ecosystem changes. Oh,
yeah. Spring's got another update. And
oh crap, I have to change these
interfaces now. Yeah, our code base
suddenly looks pretty awful. And if you
was to look through this now and and
tell me is this design or is this an
implementation choice? Is this intent or
just a how an implementation?
People would struggle to answer that.
And if you look back at the disposable
stuff, the actual useful intents, it's
very hard to work out which change came
in where. And because none of this is
version controlled, well, a lot of this
isn't version controlled compared to the
code.
So, oh yeah, docs. I forgot. See, I
forget now to talk about docs, let alone
forgetting to update the docs. Docs
falls out of place. Tests fall out of
place. Either we lack tests or we stop
running tests because they break. Um,
this is just the problem that we have
today. I'm Has anyone not experienced
this?
Just you? You. Just you.
Oh, I thought you were going to open
another can then. I really did. Um,
okay. Okay, when we go into the
maintenance cycle now, the maintenance
cycle is super painful, okay? Because
this turns into legacy code and everyone
then gets pretty afraid as to what to
touch, what, you know, whether something
is is intentional, whether something's
not intentional, if they change
something, what if that breaks something
else? It just becomes a bit of a
spaghetti. What does an AI dev tool do?
It accelerates this.
It accelerates this because these will
come in at the same speed where if we're
using AI tools to to find these issues
as well, it'll come in faster. We'll get
from this stage to this stage faster.
Okay? Because of course AI tooling
creates code for us very quickly. And of
course, we don't look at code reviews
and things like that, do we Richard? We
just accept all, push it, and if if it's
broken, Richard, someone will send the
bug fix, right?
So this is absolutely not the true
potential of AI. Okay. The true
potential of AI we believe is
specentric. And what specentcentric
means is the change we are making is the
requirements become longived. The code
becomes generated. That's huge. Whenever
we think about making these types of
things, they're made in the requirements
dock. And this only contains intent. It
only contains intent. It doesn't contain
the how. I don't care how it's built as
long as it passes these tests because
these tests validate my intent. The core
thing is a specification
is the combination of your requirements,
your intent and your tests. I've chatted
to a number of people at a number of
conferences who actually have a good
argument which is well actually your
tests are your intent because your tests
are stating how something should run.
It's the TDD method. It's TDD
methodology, right? I write my tests and
the code is just something that you
write to pass those tests. And when your
tests are satisfied, your intent is is
is satisfied. Um the code isn't then
just generated on the requirements. It's
generated on the entire spec. Okay. Um
docs no longer need to be this
descriptive thing. Docs could be
something that is also generated built
from the specification built from the
implementation potentially uh as well.
So what are we saying here? Well, we're
saying LLMs decouple the what from the
how. The intent from the implementation.
The what we can very easily describe. We
can describe it through language. We can
describe it through audio. We can
describe it through video. Maybe we can
one day do some descriptive dance to
build an application. Maybe the LLM will
take that what and it'll build that. Now
the interesting thing is as well we
don't need to be fully expressive in our
spec in our intent because actually the
LLM can actually fill in the gaps and
when we think about things like BDD
which was a wonderful a wonderful thing
back in the day one of the big things
that it needed to be was fully
descriptive of every single case but
actually the LLM's
if you say create a tic-tac-toe game it
knows what tic-tac-toe is it knows how
these types of games are built in the
past it knows what a UI looks like for
this kind of thing it fills in the gaps
So LLMs not just make specs practical
but if you think back at things that we
really liked like BDD but just really
found it hard to implement it makes
things like that practical as well.
So this is what we call AI native
development. This spec first specd
driven development where code is
generated tests are part of that
specification and part of your intent
and docs and other things like that
align. Also when you make changes let's
make a feature change let's make a a bug
change. It either changes in your actual
implementation or if it changes in your
if if it needs a change in your spec as
you write your spec it doesn't just
adapt the code per se. it can just
regenerate massive chunks of your code
as is needed.
So, let's do a demo of AI native
development.
Um, who's heard of uh a man called Dion
Almare?
A few people. Yeah, folklore says he
used to be the head of Devrell at Google
and and where else? Shopify and Augment
Code. Who's who's heard of augment code?
That's a that's a that's a pretty cool
um agentic style coding assistant. Um he
uh kind of built this he vibe coded I
think I don't know what he used maybe
bolt.new new or something like that. But
he wanted to he wanted to say how far
can we take spec driven development and
he used this over two weeks he built a P
um and this P let me take you in fact
let me take you to cursor this P is
called uh specify and
specify specify specify or specify
I think
how much you want to bet that's TC's
The first was two C's. The first version
was two.
Okay. Specify without two C's as you can
see. Um
it gives me a number of options. Um I
can create it pushes me from state to
state. I can start with a brief that
will take me to a spec. I can generate
code. I can generate tests. I can run
those tests. I can even run those
results in a rep. So for example, if I
take something like this brief, very
short brief. Um, in fact, let me take
the CLI brief and we'll use the CLI
brief. The CLI should take a string. Oh,
we recognize this. A dice notation
format D46 return the result uh um
result of the rolling the specified
number and type of dice. If no arguments
are provided, default to 1d6 and the
echo should be what is being rolled and
the result. So, rolling 1d6 would
provide five. So let's uh come down and
we'll say let's say specify oh no sorry
specify
uh brief to uh let's do brief to spec uh
and we'll pass in the brief. Uh this is
just using open gpt uh openai's gpt 40.
It's chosen a language uh JavaScript um
I think a number I'm not sure if that's
by default. I think I can change that.
Um and it's written me a specification.
in my specification
um we get a very similar output where
okay we've got a specification uh for a
component called dice roller it's got an
API it's a JavaScript API it t it's got
a function called dice roll has a
notation it's got some tests uh these
are the types of tests that we want to
run uh and some um oh and some output as
well so it's got some test types uh and
some output these are kind of like more
um validating certain things. So this is
my specification. I might want to make
changes to the specification. I might
want to generate in this case. Yes,
let's yolo it. And let's say um let's
say spec oh sorry specify
uh spec to
um let's let's run let's create some
tests. Spec to tests and we'll pass in
our spec. Now it's just going to run
it's going to create me some tests. uh
and I can then well I'll create the
implementation as well and then I'll
execute those tests against it. We can
take a quick look at the tests that are
generated
and the nice thing is I don't mind this.
One of the things is you know as we ask
it to do greater things especially like
agents and I'll show you a blog actually
that Patrick wrote recently. Um these
can take a little while and that's okay
because it's doing a far ton more than
me doing oneliners. when I do a oneliner
and I was talking to the folks at I
think it was Kodi or or maybe Tab 9.
They were talking about the amount of
time it takes them from you know from
essentially writing something from a
user writing something to something
appearing straight away and if that is
slightly slower than a number and then
you know the few hundred milliseconds
the user gets annoyed. Okay. However,
with this this can take 10 20 seconds.
When we look about Agentic, you hear
about people who kick stuff off
overnight, come back the next morning,
and that's okay because of the amount of
work it's doing. Um, so I've created
some tests. In fact, talking about let's
do spec to imple
um, and let's have a look at the tests
while that's while that's kicking off.
I'm doing the cardinal sin of spec
driven development, which is look at the
code. Um, but actually this is fine
because I'm looking at the tests and the
tests are this the tests are intent and
I'm validating that the tests are
actually testing what my intent
requests. Um, had a really interesting
comment from uh a guy uh Baroo uh when I
was in wherever it was Stockholm AI
focus really interesting new conference
that just uh that just kicked out uh
last year this year. He said to me, "An
interesting way of thinking about it is
who's heard of Girkin and cucumber BDD
style tools?" Yeah. He was talking about
creating a Girkin specification
uh whereby I describe the usual given
this then that blah blah blah and then
having cucumber run to turn that into
tests. There's no hallucinations.
There's no, you know, getting things
wrong because that is that you know it's
an LLM is nowhere near that. So all I
need to do is make sure that I I
validate the given this then that to
make sure that the tests that I am
writing are are going to be correct. In
this case though we're just yoloing it
with some LLMs. Um so yeah a bunch of
tests. Has my import been created? A
whole bunch of import but we're not
going to look at the code. We're just
going to say let's run the tests. Uh so
let's say oops spec specify
run tests
and it runs 13 passed. Uh one test file
13 tests all pass. That's quite unusual
actually. Sometimes it fails but I would
still say if they pass or fail. Let's
ship it and specify. Let's go into the
ripple. Uh in the ripple I see an
available function called dice roll. I'm
going to run dice roll passing 4d6.
So, four dice, four rolls of a six-sided
dice. Rolls two, six, two, five, total
of 15.
Yes. Um, I I I can do I can do a number
of them. So, maybe I'll say let's have
uh two rolls of a 10-sided dice, and
it'll do that. Seven and four, total 11.
Yeah. Um, I might say, now I might say,
I want to change this. change the spec.
How do I change the spec? Well,
actually, I'm in cursor right now. So,
I'm just going to say, let me grab the
spec.
Okay, I'm gonna add that. I'm gonna add
that as context. Uh,
add that as context. And I'm going to
say um
uh change my spec. What should we add so
that it makes a can opening noise every
No. So that um so so change my spec so
that it um uh shows an emoji dice
on output. I should say die, shouldn't
I? uh and doesn't
or and yeah and doesn't
doesn't show uh the individ No, let's
let's still show the individual roles
and shows the individual
roles individual roles on separate
lines.
So it's going to change my spec.
Now, what it's also doing is it's
changing my tests in my specification.
Okay, so it's it's changing what it
should expect to see. Um,
and yeah, that looks pretty good
actually. Let's apply that to my spec.
And this time I'm going to write specify
uh let's go spec uh to code. That's the
yolo.
Uh
oh, I'm in the ripple. Thank you. uh
speckle specify uh spec spec to code
which does import and tests uh and uh
spec.md.
Um now the important thing here is
because we're running through this again
everything's going to be regenerated.
Um, also by doing it with a chat, if I
have a long specification or if I have
multiple specifications, it should be
able to update all those cases, which is
another really important thing. So we
don't if it's code and we only update
one thing, okay, we forgot about these
other things. But LLMs can actually
really help us here because they know,
particularly in written language as
well, they they know what to what to
change and where. So this is a far a far
better way of uh doing that kind of
thing. Uh, so it's it's done it again.
Let's run some tests.
One fail. Nine fa nine failed. No,
sorry. Four failed. Nine passed. Ship
it. Specify ripple. I'm sure it's good
enough. Okay. Now, if I do dice roll
and pass in 4 D6.
Okay, it kind of does it. It's just the
terminal's bad at displaying this. Uh,
but it's giving me new line characters
and it's telling me dice 2, three, five,
and one, which is uh 11. Nailed it. Um,
okay. The um a core thing here as well
is LMS can take that output of failed
tests and actually change the input as
well. And of course on specify
what I could do
as well is perform a fix. And a fix will
take in my spec path. It will take in a
number of files. It will understand why
tests are failing, update the
specification or if it's a code problem
or a test problem, it will learn okay
here's the problem. I regenerate. Okay.
And it regenerates based on the output
of those problems. So it identifies
there are a few places now that these
errors could exist. But we want to make
sure that if it's a bug, the imple
changes, not the spec. If it's a problem
where with our intent, the spec changes
and then the input changes. But it's
it's core that we recognize where the
issues um exist.
Okay, I did promise one last thing. Um,
this is a native dev, um,
a, uh,
a developer site that does a number of
things, blogs, uh, podcasts, conference.
Um, Bap here does a whole bunch of
writing on it. Uh, Sammy here runs the A
Native Dev Conference. We're actually sh
Don't tell anyone. Oh, I know it's not
been announced and I'm recorded, aren't
I? H, we're going to be doing an
in-person conference in November, and
it's really close to London. is probably
about 3,000 miles away from London. So,
so keep a keep a note for November and
we'll we'll we'll be announcing more
about that um soon. Um live stream. It
will be there will be some live stream
aspects for that as well. But yeah, feel
free to register to subscribe onto this
and we'll give you a ton of news about
blogs, about the landscape, about
conference and other stuff. Um this is a
really interesting blog that Patrick
Dvois uh who knows Patrick Dvois. Yeah,
a bunch of people of course he's the uh
he's the father of DevOps. He's the
halfb brotherther of dev tooling and
he's your conference sister as well,
isn't he? Yeah. Um he's he's an amazing
guy. He's he's Belgian dude who's so up
to date on dev tooling and things like
that. But he's also one of the guys who
created DevOps days. He wrote the DevOps
handbook. He's basically one of the
people who construct in fact he coined
the name DevOps and was a massive part
of this movement. Um he's working at
Tessle. Yay. And he used to work at
Sneak with us as well for a couple of
years. Um and he wrote this he he he
went to um recently went to the AI
engineers summit in San Francisco and
wrote a blog about that. This is an
interesting one though the the rise of
parallel coding agents whereby
essentially what you do is you kick off
a ton of coding agents and you and you
see you just let them go based on
whether it's specifications based
whether it's prompts and requirements
they go off and do some stuff and then
they come back at the end and you look
at what they've each done. you can merge
them and there are tools that that
perform these workflows. Um, super super
interesting blog. Do take the time to
read it. But there are a bunch of tools
as well
here.
Um, async code agent, crystal CC
manager, split mind, claude, claude
squad, and claude code crew. These are
tools that actually do all the workflows
for you to actually perform a lot of
that parallelism and then also looking
at how they come back together at the
end. So there's a ton of stuff like this
that's also coming in in in the future
that allows us not just to run this in a
single path, but to kick it off in a
more parallel way and then identify
which which is done best. Maybe I can
merge certain things from one, certain
things from the other. There's a there's
a big future out here for effectively
having a team of agents and us being the
manager of that team to achieve what we
need.
Um,
cool. Oh I got a few more slides.
Yeah. Um, I mean, yay, I've got some
more slides. Uh okay benefits of area
native development. Um this cycle is
really really important. Now we make a
functional change to the specification.
The specification generates some code
but the key is that this validation step
this validation cycle. We have to make
sure that the code is is is a valid
representation of our specification. We
might implement in node but why stop
there? Why would anyone want to stop at
node? We don't stop at node. we go to
better implementations like Java and
other things like that based on context.
This is very this is adaptable software.
Now I might say some I might provide
some context saying the spec's fine but
here's some context to build this um
build this application on my existing
stack which is a wonderful Java stack.
Um context changes based on maintenance.
There could be a whole number of things
that I need to update on my application.
Shouldn't change the spec. It should
change the context. um other business
style things that we might want to input
whether it's policies, budget
constraints, the business needs, this
all comes in as context. It doesn't
change the specification. It changes the
way we build the target. Um, and
hopefully as agents, models get better
and better and better at writing this
code and we most importantly get better
with this validation step so that we
write the tests at every stage and every
code changes goes through all those
tests. We should be able to say generate
it, make it faster, improve security,
whatever our context requires, feed it
back, validate it back to the
specification and then spit out some
node generated node uh image. Of course,
we're going to stop there as well. Once
we get to system telemetry, once we go
into production, how is this actually
acting in production? Let me take those
signals, take those flags, send it back
as context, and regenerate. My spec
doesn't change because this is specific
to that implementation. This is specific
to the environment it's going in. This
could be used by hundreds of different
people that have different context
requirements to the same specification.
Of course, this makes software
development much much more inclusive
because I as a developer today
not all of my skills are going to be as
useful in this new world because
actually my coding skills become less
interesting. But my knowledge of being a
developer for 20 something years now
has built me this knowledge of this
wisdom of knowing how to deploy, knowing
what good architecture looks like,
knowing what good design is, knowing how
to deploy something to scale. And all of
this means if we want to build a real
enterprise production style environment,
yes, anyone can build, anyone can do
this. We sim vibe coding. Anyone can
just type a few things in. But we need
that experience, that ingrained
experience that we have learned over
years to say this is what good
architecture looks like. We need a good
PM body to say these are the things that
the user needs. Okay, we'll have a ton
of different people who can do this. But
together with that knowledge, that
wisdom, that experience, we'll be able
to build this build this application
more. But it will be a more inclusive
space. there are a ton of questions that
we don't know the answer to but at
Tessle we're trying to look through
answer through the community um
and the most important thing is AI
native is a new development paradigm we
can't think about it in the same way as
we thinking about code generated uh uh
sorry codeentric for example how do you
version adaptable implementations if you
have a version of a spec and then you
have a number of implementations all
that have different different revisions
through context changes. How do you make
sure that that version repres that that
version of the code, that version of the
implementation references the version of
the spec it came from, but triggers up
every single time? There there are there
are a ton of questions here because
we're in a new paradigm we need to think
about much more deeply. Um, and an
interesting one at the bottom there on
the right, what is the role of an AI
native developer? We've got some ideas.
Developers will absolutely still be
around. This isn't an AI world that is
just, you know, yolo go. It is for a
disposable application. If I wanted an
interrupt every five seconds, I'll
either call you or I'll write this
application, but I'm not putting that
into production, right? There's a ton of
there's a ton of reasons why I wouldn't
put that in production as Matt as Matt
talked through, right? But it's as a
disposable app. It's amazing.
Is that me? Oh, no. A few a couple more.
I promise a couple more. A Tessle. Yeah,
we This is what we're working on. The
spec the specify that's just a it's not
even open source. It's just a it's just
a literally a yolo style. What can we do
with this? But at at Speckle at Tessle,
we are building something a framework, a
platform that will allow you to do all
these types of things. And we we're not
doing it by ourselves. We believe this
is an open space where every single AI
vendor, every single person who's trying
to build AI tooling should be able to
integrate, should be able to connect and
provide their value in as a step, as a
component in this workflow to be able to
say, "Oh, you want to do documentation
with swim, you want to do testing with
Kodo, that's fine. Let's add these as as
as parts of our workflow, but we need
this workflow to be end to end." And
this is this is one of the things that
we're that we're building. The AI native
landscape, as mentioned, can I click on
that? I can. AI native landscape as
mentioned is an amazing resource where
you can actually look through a whole
ton of various AI native and AI dev
tools. Um, feel free to go there. It's
an open- source repo. So, feel free to
send pull requests. There's some Google
forms there if you wanted to if you
wanted to add in tools that you use or
or have built as well. We'll we'll
definitely uh accept those. Um, and I
think
Oh my gosh, where's it gone?
I think
well it absolutely is the end of the
presentation because I can't get this
back. Uh so
there we go. I'm pretty sure the next
one's Thank you. Thank you.
[Applause]
Um I went to touch over. If anyone wants
to if anyone needs to go, if anyone
wants to grab a beer, please do. But any
questions?
Sir, I have one question. So it seems
like I I I think this is the right sort
of way to do this. The one part where
I'm not this question is for instance
you have a a setup and you have you want
a a change right
would you have would you need to kind of
say okay I need to go change the spec
and then the test and then drive the
development or would you want to do it
the other way i.e. go update the code
which is already based on a set of tests
that should run and then you check what
you have and if that is if that's
correct then go back and update the spec
because it seems a bit again wasteful if
I may in a wide coding kind of world
where actually I may not even want to
accept 15 of these changes and only get
to a point where this is what I want to
do. Mhm. Yeah, really great question. So
the question was so first of all a
comment just to say you think it's the
right path. You said the session was
amazing. Um
you said if a change needed to be made
would it be better to go and change the
the code itself and either then make a
change back to the spec or if I may have
a system recognize the change in the
test in the in the code to actually
suggest a change to make to the
specification. I'm saying
I do believe that the spec should
change. Actually, I do agree with that.
I think this is the right way to do
this. I'm just questioning is it spec
change first and code or is it code
change? No, it's okay. You go back and
then update. And the question and and
the addition I was making is if you only
change the code, you could actually have
the system recognize what you're
changing and suggest a change to the
spec. So, it's another Yeah, it I I
think it's completely valid. number one.
Um, number two is I think if you make
the change to the code,
it requires someone who is very
understanding of the code. Number one,
um, I think that's easy if you have
existing developer teams right now that
own specific components and so forth. I
believe as we evolve more into the spec
world, that won't happen as much. We
will actually detach ourselves from the
code. today though where we are still
very code savvy where people sometimes
will find it faster actually as well to
make a code change I think that's
reasonable but I think it's only
reasonable if when you make that change
back to the spec it generates the code
that is in a in a similar way because if
I make a change to my specification and
it makes a completely different change
then I might have to then go ahead
because it might think oh actually I
might refactor some certain things
because there may actually be a more
performant way of doing things and etc
etc. So, it's a perfect perfectly valid
way of doing it. It's just a choice and
today people who are more comfortable
going into the code would make that
choice. But yeah, I think both are valid
um so long as we don't drop into that
that place where code we're making code
changes without making an update to the
spec because then the code immediately
becomes a source of truth. Yeah. I mean,
I think that the back stop is a 100%
100%. Yeah. Yeah.
Yep. Agree. Anyone else have thoughts on
that? Agree with that? Yeah. Uh, sorry.
Why don't you go first? Uh, about that
to the
You were waiting for me to crack that
then, weren't you? I saw
I tried to make it available because it
looks um the specified tool. Yeah, it
was super interesting. It was just two
weeks old. Uh, sorry, not two weeks old.
It took two weeks to build. It was vibe
coded. There are probably a million
things that are wrong with it. Um, and
we're actually building a far more
expensive version of that tool. Uh,
which if you follow tesla.io, uh, you'll
absolutely get, you know, early access
to. But this is the style. This is the
type of thing that that we are um that
we're looking at at building in in this
kind of way. We wanted to build we
wanted to build it. We wanted to build
it in a much more production ready way
with a whole ton of other things which,
you know, we're going through private
meter now. So, if you're interested,
ping me an email. Simon at tesl.io and
I'll help you get onto that early access
program and you can give us feedback.
We're hoping not long now and we can
hopefully be open beta. Um but yeah,
absolutely. That's just a that was just
a yolo kind of uh vibe coding thing. You
don't want to you don't want to go fully
production with that. You want something
more well built.
No problem. Yeah. Um you spoke about Oh,
I think an important bit was that the
skill of of the developer for
won't go away. Now we you mentioned that
the the spec itself through giving a lot
of examples through requirements. So I
as a user want to do this when I do
this. Could that then transform to
actually an architectural record of I
want components that are cohesive and I
want things in my code to be like uh
decoupled in this way and then this so
that that is the spec flow of how the
system is designed with with context in
reference to changing requirements. Yeah
really great question. So, um I'm not
sure I'm going to be able to repeat that
whole thing, but uh it was all really
about how the the architecture of that
application
uh is defined, whether it's in the spec
or maybe even a a sidespec or something
that defines an application. And and I
think I think yeah, absolutely that the
the the ability for us to break down
components in a certain way where we
know it's the right way of doing it
through our design, AI can have a good
crack at that. Sometimes it would be
right, sometimes it would be wrong. But
it it does need context because actually
I would architect if I have different
business needs and different deployment
needs, I'd architect my application in a
different way and I'd actually compose
my my my components in such a way
whereby that would be possible for
people to do that fairly easily. So
today we know how to to architect how to
construct and design applications that
it's reusable so that things are
services and things work well together.
the
at Tesla we're looking at if you if you
ask something we break this down into a
number of different steps and components
and stages. Um now that might be right
it might be wrong. It's important to be
able to then give feedback into that to
say I want this to look more like this.
I want the APIs between these components
to work like this. And you're doing that
because you actually have the the wisdom
and I think it's important to use that
word the wisdom through experience to
know what good design and what good
architecture looks like. And that's the
bit that we as developers will will
provide into this new process. The
understanding of how good applications
are built. The other piece, the
capabilities for example, this is what
good PMs are good at. This is what good
people who can describe a good
requirements part says these are the
things I care about. And actually the
bottleneck almost sits there because as
this be as we're able to deliver fast,
how much do we deliver? How much user
feedback do we get? How do we iterate on
this application? you the the a good PM
will be very clearly distinct from a bad
PM there who delivers too much of a bad
thing without enough feedback and things
like that. But yeah, there's a number of
roles like that. Did that answer your
question? It did. There's a number of
roles like that that are important so
that if you have a good PM style you um
persona a good developer architect
persona and developers will need to
level up into that architect design
space and other other people who know
what good intent and what good you know
not necessarily defining exactly what
performance looks like and things like
that because the LLMs can learn those
types of things but recognizing the the
nonfunctional parts and building that in
is is super super important. Uh I think
you had next um something I wasn't
completely sure on. Yeah. Clarity is
yeah in in that model when you're
changing the spec disposable is the code
is it all regenerated every time? Yeah
great question. Can it can it be
incremental? So is it is it effectively
a mutable code that you throw away and
regenerate? Great question. So the
question was um every time you iterate
on the on the specification how uh
disposable is the existing code from the
previous version of the spec to the new
does it rewrite the whole thing or does
it does it just update so I think one
important thing is and one of the things
that we're kind of like going through
the process of learning as well is it's
important to document I think the ways
in which when we when we when we create
an implementation when we generate what
decisions are made because whether it's
a decision that we made or a decision
that an NLM We might say actually that's
a really interesting decision. I want to
promote that up to the to my main
specification or maybe it should be part
of I don't know I'm going to say the
word shadow spec here which maybe sits
underneath the specification that
captures a bunch of decisions that the
LLM made. It's more implementation
decisions. Um what we don't want is a
complete regeneration every single time
because actually then we're just going
to keep spinning the dice, keep rolling
the dice until oh finally all my tests
have passed now. when actually what I
really want is understand which parts of
my codebase needs to change make those
changes only and actually you know
breaking everything down into super
modular spaces helps this significantly.
Um, and if you do need to regenerate,
you know, amounts of this, regenerate it
with this almost this shadow spec in
mind so that it uses past decisions that
the user didn't make but the previous
LLMs did so that we don't actually see
changes in behavior so that that button
doesn't change from blue to black such
that implement the way implementations
are built doesn't mean that oh these
unit tests are now rubbish I have to
respin and create new imple new unit
tests for this method. we want to limit
that as much as possible by learning
from what we're what we built the
previous time. So yeah, I think that's
it's a however it's done, whether it's a
shadow spec that captures information,
whether we use code as context uh in our
change, whether we try and break it down
so that everything's so small you
actually only regenerate parts of the
code. There are a number of ways it
could be done, but I think what you're
state that the problem you're stating is
very much top of mind for people who are
doing this regeneration. Yeah, there
isn't one answer. I I don't think
there's one answer and I don't think
there's one correct way, but I think
there's it's definitely a thing that we
can't we can't um
we can't leave to this deter this
non-determinism whereby it just changes
every time. like the the idea of
composing your application into a ton of
components whereby actually they're so
small you actually just only need to
change you need to identify which
components you need to change and just
respin those blocks. Yeah. Exactly.
Exactly. Yeah. Yeah. And again a lot of
that is through architecture choices and
things like that. Yeah.
And I'm going to reformulate the same
question I asked at the end of the
previous talk like M in this scenario in
which at the end uh you're going to talk
with the LLM there is the problem with
the context window again
like what's your idea about how what is
the unit for a spec like with a growing
project like is it going to be one for
everything how do you
going to split it not don't transfer the
no no I'll use the same answer whatever
the whatever the answer was I use the
same answer no no I hear Another small
question next to it is like does it make
sense to add to the specs uh some really
specific personas like
define the tasks like developer the box
things like this specific.
Yeah. Yeah. Great question. Um so first
question it absolutely makes sense to
break everything down. Um the way we see
it is if you was to provide me with a
brief that has a you know a huge um a hu
that has you know a much greater task I
might say well actually I'm going to
create a top level spec and then for
every component that I have underneath
I'm effectively creating a tree of
components. Every component then has its
own specification its own API and its
own set of tests. Then if I want to make
a change, I make a change just to the
specification that I'm calling. Each of
those each of those each of the parent
components that use that that that
smaller component, they're the now the
integration tests for that. And the
tests that exist in there are kind of
like a little bit more unit test style
for this for this component. Um, and
this is super important because as we
ship, we don't want to ship it as one.
We want to ship it as every single unit
that is actually reusable. If you wanted
to maybe create another app and actually
you don't need to rebuild all these
extra things. You might say that that
component there I want to use it as is
and this one and this one and this one
because half of what we build as
developers we write glue code. That's
that's what we do right half of what we
do is out there already and open source
and other things. We're building on that
so so much. We just need to effectively
write these few things and then 80% of
our code base is borrowed or used. So
that's if we if we're not doing that
then we're breaking some of our biggest
gains in the last 20 years of software
development. Uh your second question was
like having more practical
oh personas.
Yeah I think that's really interesting
and I think um I think
yeah I think I think we from this point
of view I don't think it matters whether
you're specentric or codecentric. I
think you know it's exactly that similar
case whereby you know maybe you have
different agents looking and they have a
different background and that different
uh that different way of looking at the
code. Maybe you have a tester a tester
persona that's looking at building out
those those those test cases. I think
that's we're using from at that point
we're using all the best practices that
we learned from using LLMs. I don't
think it makes sense. And I'd even go
further. I'd even say don't just stop at
personas
have different models. use different
models for generating code, different
models for creating specs, different
different models for generating your
tests. Uh each of these models are good
at different things. Uh or even
different flavors of the of the same
model uh or or or group of models from a
certain provider. Um we change
everything based on what is best for
this task.
Uh were you? Yeah, I think you next.
Yeah. So I mean some of some of this was
already touched on, but basically we
like this hierarchy of specs, right?
Maybe on the top is like the company
mission statement just says do it. Yeah.
Yeah. Just deliver on that 10% grow and
then you kind of go down like for a big
company there would be all these kind of
like departments and groups and products
and and then I guess that's that's
that's yeah I wouldn't I wouldn't
necessarily say it's a it's a tree that
big. I would say it's kind of nice to to
continue to be fairly shallow in terms
of what we're building. I think it gets
it gets too unmanageable the more depth
and the greater this whole thing is. Um
I think we as developers will actually
start broadening ourselves massively and
understanding huge parts of the
application that we wouldn't normally
look at but I still see these as
actually much smaller units applications
I think will probably I mean I don't
know if they will change mass size
massively but I think I think keeping
them similar size I don't I don't see
necessarily uh the need to change that.
I think it is good to though share
decisions that are made as business
decisions or things that should be uh
reused. Um, like I love the I love the
comment I think it was about prompts
being shared. Like a ton of people do
that like Kodi have this prompt library
where you can actually store prompts and
I think AI engineering teams I mentioned
this to someone in the hall. AI AI
engineering teams are able to say this
is the prompt library and my teams can
use various prompts a good prompt that
makes me create tests in a good way. Um,
exactly the same like we should be there
should be things we share but
applications can still be you know I
don't want to say pizza box or pizza
order what's the whatever the phrase is
two pizza teams that kind of you know
size I mean I guess the worries then
within you might get like much more
optimized local maximum so like one team
would kind of hyper optimize for their
case to the detriment the rest of the
business whereas that's that's how we
design and we architect the application
Right? We can't just let the LLM do what
it whatever it wants. We need to be in
control of the LLM. We can't be the
LLM's agent. The the agents need to work
for us. So if the agent's doing
something that we disagree with from an
architecture point of view, a
maintenance point of view, a company
team point of view, we change it and we
tell it, "No, no, this is wrong." Uh
whether it's just the architecture of
the app or the way it's trying to build
multiple applications. Yeah, that that's
on us. That's uh that's us except alling
then.
Cool. Cool. One last question and then
or maybe we do one in the hall. Uh oh
no, it's Farath. He's gonna ask a really
hard question. Thank you everyone for uh
No, go on Fath. Go on.
I've been seeing stuff about like wise
and software that adapts to the user.
Yeah. Uh how would like a static spec
how would that fit into a world where
the software changes the user? So yeah,
the way the user changes it or they ask
for it to appear in a certain way. How
would a static spec if that's what
you're maybe notic
well I don't I don't think it needs to
be a static spec if if we try and
compare a spec centric versus a
codecentric in exactly the same way
would you consider the code to be static
there's multiple uses right
so you'd have you'd have a different
spec for each person
how you thought about this before no
it's not it's definitely not a use case
I've thought about uh it's a good
question though really good question Um
yeah, I haven't even thought. What would
you think?
Um
I I guess the the points about
modularity in small pieces kind of kind
of made some sort of sense. Um maybe
yeah having that sort of depending on
how the user is using the soft
implementing certain parts of it but
then change other parts some sort of
memory like open AI has some sort of
memory. Yeah. and some sort of memory
there that this person likes to use
their software in this sle.
I love the OSGI model. If we take you
back about 20 years, the OSGI model of
being able to whatever whatever pieces
of software you drop in at the time, it
reacts to it live and kind of like
spawns things up and does things like
that. These are these are kind of like
using some of those old techniques to
kind of like spawn things up and change
the way things look just by dropping
things in based on user needs and things
like that. We can probably learn from
things like that as well. But yeah, not
definitely not a use case I've thought
about. Anyone else thought about that
kind of use case.
See, you're you're a trailblazer.
We were going to write a piece about
this like the the new age of interfaces
and what they would look like. So there
we go. Aative dev.io/ io/blog.
Bab's going to answer that question in a
blog. No, we we need you to write that
piece for us. Yeah. Yeah. There we go.
F. We've sorted it. You're going to
write that post for us, Bap, and then
it's going to be there. Cool. Thank you
so much. Really appreciate it. Let's
grab some more beers and chat in the in
the corridor.